From the hel vector to a flying
platform, from a steam powered rocket
belt to a revolutionary jetpack,
these are the secret weapon systems
developed to put a soldier in the sky to
give American troops a deadly advantage
over the communists.
These rarelyseen films reveal the race
to create a lethal new line of weapons.
>> It's a deadly little machine.
>> Right now on World's Weirdest Weapons,
we're going behind the scenes on the
quest for the flying soldier.
Since the invention of the airplane, the
military has tried to crack the problem
of putting individual soldiers in the
sky.
Nowhere is that need more clear than in
the rugged terrain of the Korean War.
It's the start of a top secret program.
In the early 1950s, the US Army is
locked in combat with the Communists in
North Korea.
It's a terrible place for fighting.
Rocky ground,
exposed valleys,
lethal minefields.
It's no battlefield for trucks or jeeps.
The solution is to take to the air.
But military helicopters aren't good
enough.
They had big limitations. They weren't
effective in difficult terrain,
difficult climate, primitive operating
conditions, and helicopters simply
weren't very reliable.
To win the war against the communists,
mobility on the battlefield has to
improve.
So within the US Army, another idea
takes hold.
Could individual soldiers be given the
power to fly?
If you could have an aerial equivalent
of a cavalryman's horse, you would have
a new kind of warfare.
It's an idea that will obsess the
military for the next two decades.
They want a machine as simple to control
as a motorcycle.
Aeronautical genius Charles H. Zimmerman
is convinced the secret to the flying
soldier lies in our natural ability to
balance.
>> It started out as a thought exercise
where he actually was balancing a
[music] pencil and assuming that he was
the pencil, what would happen as he was
balancing it on his tilting hand. So he
would move it back and forth and say,
"What would happen if that was me?"
Zimmerman tests his idea with a board
balancing on a jet of pressurized air.
The pilot uses body movement to control
the board much like a surfer does on
water. That's the theory, but this
device is attached to an air hose. How
can it be made to fly under its own
power?
Rotor blades are a possible solution,
but not in a conventional way. If the
blades are on top, there are problems.
>> If you were to have a device like this
where the rotor was on top and the
center of gravity was below basically
the pilot, if it were to tilt in this
direction, in order to write it, the
pilot would have to move forward. And
this is actually backwards from the way
everybody else thinks.
Zimmerman's principle only works if you
put the rotors underneath
[music]
>> when you reverse the direction. So that
now the center of gravity is above where
the pilot is standing. If the device
tilts forward, the natural tendency of
the pilot [music] would be to pull back
on the handlebars essentially shift his
weight aft and correct that.
>> The result is the heltor.
It even has floats so it can land on
water.
And just as Zimmerman predicted, it can
be steered by leaning one way or the
other.
>> If the vehicle were to tilt to the left
or tilt to the right, once again, the
handlebars would go in this direction
and then the pilot's natural tendency
would be to go in the other direction
and to bring it back.
>> It looks like a simple machine for a
flying soldier.
But there is one terrible flaw. It's too
slow for the battlefield.
>> At 20 mph, you're pretty much a sitting
duck for anybody with a rifle.
>> And if the enemy don't get you, there's
a good chance you'll kill yourself.
Those rotor blades are lethal.
>> Basically, you're standing on top of a
very large blender that's powered by
maybe 80 horsepower. So you don't want
to have any part of your body
accidentally fall into the rotors.
>> In fact, anything falling into the
rotors would be catastrophic.
And trees or high obstacles pose another
threat. It's only really safe flying
across open terrain.
No use in a place like Korea. The
helctor had a 30foot diameter, so you
had to keep your rotor disc from
striking the ground. And as a matter of
fact, that did happen at one point that
in forward flight, they struck the
ground. The rotors collapsed and the
device, you know, unfortunately
disintegrated.
The risks are too high.
After a couple of near fatal crashes,
the helicar project is shelved.
But the engineers continue to
experiment, looking for a safer way to
keep a flying platform in the air.
In California, a promising new design is
being developed by Stanley Hiller.
This time, the rotor blades are safely
tucked away in a fan.
This meant that you could fly in an
environment where there were things like
tree branches or confinement and not
strike that rotating propeller.
>> Hiller also makes his device as simple
to control as possible.
>> Well, it feels fine and the nice thing
about it is very easy to fly. Uh what do
you think, Phil, is the truly
revolutionary characteristic of this
machine? We have the throttle which all
aircraft have but uh we control it by
shifting our weight using our feet.
>> It's the Zimmerman principle again
using body movement to maneuver the
device.
>> This is the Hiller flying platform. It's
simple, ingenious, and rugged.
The thrust keeping the platform aloft
comes from two propellers powered by
separate 40 horsepower engines.
>> Both engines feed a contraotating
mechanism that spins one propeller
clockwise and the other propeller
counterclockwise. This is to make a
smooth column of air to lift the
platform without any turbulence.
>> The engines are as simple to start as a
lawn mower.
The curved shape of the fan also helps
to keep the platform in the air.
>> As the air is being drawn by the
propellers, it passes over this ducted
fan surface. This actually creates a
lift combined with the thrust to propel
the flying platform on a column of air.
>> The early tests impress the military.
The idea of the flying platform was
really appealing because it was a small
lightweight device that could be easily
transported and flown by a non-pilot.
>> Interest is so great that Hiller decides
to reveal his top secret device to the
public.
>> This was the realization of a flying
carpet. So this was the beginning of all
of the Johnny Quest and Jetsons and
everyone else who wanted to fly. This
was the inspiration. [music]
The Hiller flying platform went from
being top secret to on everyone's
Christmas wish list. This is an example
of one of the toys. This was actually
made in the 50s and it demonstrates
flying on a column of air. No batteries
required.
The Hiller platform looks like the
answer for the US Army's flying soldier,
but there's one flaw in the design.
It's just not reliable.
>> One engine failure would cause
catastrophic event.
If either engine fails, both platform
and pilot would drop like a stone, and
they're flying too low for any parachute
to open.
So for safety, they add on a backup
engine.
>> So you actually had a layer cake of
three propellers and three engines.
But that third engine makes the platform
so heavy it can no longer be controlled
by a soldier just shifting his weight.
There were so many engines and so many
propellers that they now needed
aerodynamic surfaces and the skills of a
pilot to fly it.
>> The platform is no longer the simple
flying device the US Army needs.
But if this technology doesn't work for
individual flight, could it power an
even more ambitious vision?
The army's ultimate go anywhere vehicle,
a flying jeep.
They wanted to be able to cross rivers,
go over hills, go places where there
weren't roads, and do it quickly and
safely.
Just like the Hiller flying platform, it
uses rotors encased in a fan. But to
lift its much heavier weight, the jeep
has two fans with seats in between.
So the soldiers don't have to sit
directly above [music] the deadly
blades.
The main benefit to having the ducks for
and half of a cockpit is so that I don't
have to worry about my equipment falling
into them and causing us to crash.
What we now have is a control stick and
this manipulates aerosurfaces in order
to get basically the control that the
pilot wants.
This particular aircraft used about 360
horsepower in order to lift its bulk in
what little payload it could.
And the Jeep does fly even reaching
speeds of up to 65 m an hour.
But it takes a trained pilot to stay in
control.
>> This is not an easy vehicle to fly. And
in fact, it had some quirks that made it
um a challenge.
>> And it was a gas guzzler. It could only
fly about 25 m on one tank.
>> Even with a fair amount of power, it
really wasn't very efficient.
This fanpowered technology just isn't
going to deliver a flying soldier for
the army.
They continue their quest, looking for
another power source able to lift a
soldier into the air.
They turn their attention from rotors to
rockets.
But harnessing rocket power to a
personal flying machine is not going to
be easy.
Then in the late 1950s, the US Army
hears about some intriguing experiments
[music] at Bell Aeros Systems.
This individual lifting device is
clearly in its early days.
But Wendell Moore, Bell's leading rocket
engineer, is convinced his machine will
be the [music] future of individual
flight.
His inspiration comes from one of the
fastest airplanes in the world, Bell's
rocket powered XPlane,
the first aircraft to break the sound
barrier.
To keep the Xplane stable at high
altitude, Wendell Moore designs a set of
miniature rockets. He had developed a
series of thrusters that could control
the X1 as it made its transition into
supersonic flight.
>> Thrust from these mini rockets can lift
the wings up or push them down as
needed.
Wendell Moore wonders if they can also
lift a man into the air.
>> So, he's sitting under the wing of the
mother plane in the shade out there in
the desert one day and he says to uh one
of his co-workers, he said, "You know, I
could take a couple of these small
thrusters and put them on a man he could
fly like Buck Rogers." And he drew an
idea in in in the gravel. And um so when
he got back he started doing some
research and it seemed that the the uh
military was interested in such a thing.
>> But these mini rockets are powered by a
highly dangerous chemical
pure hydrogen peroxide.
As the peroxide passes over a silver
catalyst, it explodes
in a massive burst of superheated steam.
Harnessing this incredibly powerful
force to a man's back is going to be
[music] a challenge
at Bell's headquarters. Wendell Moore
doesn't even dare to use this peroxide
in his early experiments.
Moore's [music]
technology of hydrogen peroxide is very
difficult to handle. So pressurized gas
is readily available. You simply have a
large tank and you can fly for many
minutes to [music] get training
experience.
>> That's the theory. But even controlling
this experimental rig is not easy.
>> They had two or three men holding the
ropes that were tied around the guy's
waist so that they wouldn't lose
control.
Kathleen's father, Tom Lennon, was
Belle's in-house cameraman. [music]
He photographed the engineer's struggle
to stay upright.
>> My father, just [music] seeing it
through the lens of his camera, asked if
he could make a suggestion. So he um he
put the rig on and he said if you would
just keep your legs your feet pinned
together it would be like the rudder of
a boat or the tail wing on an airplane
and that would give you some stability.
[music]
>> With this technique, Tom Lennon stays in
control for up to 3 minutes.
>> I think it came down to the fact, do you
believe you can fly or don't you? And
[music]
if you do believe it, you can.
>> By 1960, [music] the army believe that
Wendell Moore may have the solution for
their flying soldier.
They give him $150,000,
equivalent to about a million in today's
money, to build his [music] rocket belt.
It's a flying backpack powered by
hydrogen peroxide.
It uses pressurized gas to force the
peroxide up into a small chamber filled
with silver mesh just behind the
soldier's head.
As the peroxide hits the silver
catalyst,
there's an explosive burst of
superheated steam. When you have water
heated to 1388°,
you instantly have 5,000 times the
volume in superheated steam
and it has to go somewhere or you have
an explosion.
So, it's exhausted out the two nozzles
and that's where you get your thrust.
[music]
This superheated steam produces about
a,00 horsepower.
Enough thrust to lift 300 lb of man and
machine.
>> Most people are afraid of the heat
generated by a rocket belt, but really
it's no more than would be generated by
a motorcycle exhaust.
>> And just like a motorcycle, you can use
a throttle to adjust the power.
But that doesn't make it easy to fly.
These early test films show the pilots
are still using safety ropes.
>> The biggest danger was falling. Gravity
was the biggest enemy of the rocket
belt.
>> If things do go wrong, it has no wings
to help it glide to the ground.
>> We had company doctors and they were
getting increasingly worried and we had
some elements of our management who were
nervous Nellies.
Bell's management are so concerned about
the risks, they want to close the
project down,
but Wendell Moore isn't the type of man
to give in.
>> Everyone who knew Wendell knew him as
the indominable spirit. He would work on
things and he'd get his mind into
something and he was not easily stopped.
Moore tries to make his device safe.
[music]
The key is to make it easier to control.
So, he changes the hand controls to
twist grips like on a motorcycle.
One to alter direction left or right,
the other to control the throttle.
And to direct the thrust more easily, he
adds a [music] pivot to the control
arms.
>> The pivot actually allowed you to steer
it somewhat like a motorcycle. [music]
So if you wanted to go forward, you
could depress it. If you wanted to turn
bank left or bank right, you could
simply turn the handlebars to do that.
>> By April 1961, Wendel Moore's rocket
belt is ready to make aviation history.
27year-old test pilot Hal Graham
prepares to make his first free flight
without any safety ropes.
It lasts just 13 seconds, a second
longer than the Wright brothers first
flight.
Hal Graham stays in the air for only 112
ft. But it proves that Wendell Moore's
rocket [music] belt can fly.
>> Hal Graham described his first flight
like a gentle giant picking him up by
the back and carry him across a field
and setting him down gently.
Up until that time, he had been tethered
by wires and constrained by people
holding safety ropes on him. He said
when he was actually free, he found it
much simpler to fly than in training.
Bell are keen to show off their device
as soon as possible to the army, but
Wendel Moore insists on more secret
tests.
He wants to make sure the rocket belt is
reliable, safe, and easy to maneuver.
One lesson they learn is how to manage
the thrust from the rocket engine. As
soon as you crack the valve open, the
valve actually throttles the system to
70%. Which makes you weightless. You're
already floating off the ground.
The remaining 30% of throttle allows you
to maneuver. So whether you want to
climb or accelerate forward, you have
that 30% in reserve.
It takes another 28 flights before he
decides that the rocket belt is ready
for its greatest test, a demonstration
flight in front of the army.
In early June 1961, the Army's dream of
a flying soldier seems about to come
true.
Rocket Belt pilot Howal Graham prepares
to demonstrate this top secret flying
device to the army for the first time.
It's a nervous moment for the Bell team.
After years of development, they don't
want anything to spoil the big day.
It's a triumph for Wendel Moore's rocket
belt.
News of the rocket belt success soon
reaches the army's top brass.
Just a week later, they invite Hal
Graham to fly the rocket belt at the
Pentagon
in front of over 3,000 senior officers
and staff.
It's another massive day for Wendel
Moore.
The pressure is on. His rocket belt has
to deliver.
[music]
It looks like the army finally has its
flying soldier.
In October 1961, the commanderin-chief
himself, [music] President John F.
Kennedy, comes to Fort Bragg, North
Carolina.
He's a passionate believer in the power
of technology.
Only 6 months before he set America on
its path to the moon. Now he wants to
see his army's latest weapons.
The flying soldier is one of the star
turns making a perfect flight from ship
to shore.
A local [music] paper reports the
president was wideeyed and openmouthed
just like a kid.
Everything is looking good for the
rocket belt. But once the excitement
dies down, the reality kicks in.
It may work like science fiction, but
for the military, there are two major
issues.
First and most serious is that the belt
can only stay in the air for 21 seconds.
>> The key limitation of any rocket system
is that you can deliver a lot of power,
but you can't carry very much fuel and
so your endurance is extremely limited.
>> The rocket belt consumes 2 1/2 lb of
fuel every second.
if they carried more than about 20
seconds or so of fuel that it became so
heavy that you couldn't literally stand
with it on your back.
>> The second issue is that the army is not
convinced that the device is simple
enough for an ordinary soldier to fly.
Wendle and all of us were very conscious
of the fact that one of the limiting
factors would be how much training was
it going to take to teach a man how to
fly.
>> In the early 1960s the confrontation in
Vietnam is ramping up.
>> The US Air Force trained South
Vietnamese pilots to supply isolated
outposts in a land where roads are all
too few.
This seems perfect terrain for the
flying soldier, especially as it's
increasingly likely the American
infantry will soon be heavily involved.
So Wendel Moore continues to try to
convince the army that an average rookie
GI can fly his rocket belt.
He needs to find an unskilled young man
of draft age.
In 1964,
one of his neighbors, William Suttor,
was that young man.
As a kid, I used to do odd jobs for him,
mainly cutting the lawn. I used to say
to him, you know, Wendell, when are you
going to get me a job flying a
Rockefell? And he he said, "Oh, there'll
be one coming. There'll be one coming."
>> Wendell Moore almost misses his chance.
>> I ran into Wendell in the grocery store
and he said, "How's it going, Willie?
What's going on?" I said, "Oh, I quit
school and I'm joining the army." And he
said, "Oh, no, no, no. Wait. I got a job
for you flying the rocket belt."
>> For 19-year-old William Suttor, flying
this rocket belt is a dream opportunity.
>> When you're that age, a lot of the
thoughts of [music] mortality don't
cross your mind. The joy, the adventure,
the wow factor, you know, holy Christ,
I'm going to strap a rocket and fly.
But he still has to learn how to control
that rocket to show the army anyone can
do it.
>> The rocket belt produces about a
thousand horsepower which is strapped to
your body. So it's extremely easy to
over control and that's the hardest
thing to learn is to not over control
the machine.
>> He is soon leaving the safety ropes
behind and flying free.
You open that throttle and you know
there's all this heat coming off the
ground and then as soon as you lift off
the heat disappears
and your actions are almost intuitive.
The rocket belt was unbelievably
controllable.
You could uh I called it thread the
needle with the thing.
William Suttor is now ready to join the
Bell team, shooting a promotional film
to show the military what the rocket
belt can do for them.
We wanted to take Remington 1100
semi-automatic shotguns, take the stock
off and mount actual shotguns on here
with tracer rounds. But the powers to
be, they they said, "No way. We're not
arming you with actual weapons.
But what they do get are miniature
rockets.
Their mission is to fire these rockets
at an enemy bunker.
You have the power of flight just like a
bird. And a bird doesn't think what
they're doing. They just do it. So I
knew I had to come around the bunker,
face the door, but not leave myself open
as an easy target. You know,
theoretically there was somebody in
there that was after me and I was after
them. I came around and I just slid
sideways in front of the the doorway and
as I slid on by, I fired one off
and then just another tweak and I was
gone in the other direction.
>> His next mission is to target a jeep.
>> The rockets were on the side here and no
matter where you face, that's where the
rocket was going to go.
I know on one of them I put it right in
the rear window of the Jeep
and it bounced off the rear view mirror
and the windshield,
but it it you know it it is a deadly
little machine, you know, when used
properly.
Now the team has to show how a rocket
belt can take soldiers to places they
would never have gone before.
This is the American rapids just above
the American Falls at Niagara. Can you
imagine trying to get your troops across
here?
Boats would be no good, but we have the
Bell Rocket belt. So, we bring them over
by rocket belt. We did this flight to
show the army that it was a great way to
overcome natural barriers.
Before
attempting the flight over the water, we
made a flight over the pedestrian
bridge. If we didn't have enough time to
get across, we could land on the bridge.
There was no problem timewise. Then we
moved upstream here. And it's a little
narrower here even and made the flight
across safely. It took about 11 seconds
to cross.
Next [music] up is a reconnaissance
mission along the Niagara River Gorge.
[music]
Flying down here in the gorge was some
of the most fun and the spectacular
scenery. And to go out over these
cliffs,
you have instant altitude. The gorge
here is over 300 ft deep. It It was, you
know, a once in a-lifetime experience
really. His
rapid progress with the rocket belt
[music] is proof to the army that a
19-year-old rookie can be trained to
fly.
They saw the rocket belt having the same
requirements of all military things that
you can handy- [music]
recruit a device. They strap it on and
they use it. And in this case, that
means [music] that they can fly over a
canyon, fly over a minefield, uh trail a
telephone wire.
>> But there remains one serious practical
issue. The rocket belt still has only 21
seconds of flying time.
I once during the making of that film
stepped off a 300 foot cliff and I
didn't fire the rocket up until after I
was off and starting down in order to
save precious seconds. You know, at the
other end of the flight,
you were looking for your landing site
and thinking about landing.
You know, a place like this is nowhere
to run out of fuel or or even, you know,
a couple of feet off the ground. And
I've had it run out and uh you know your
feet sting a bit, but not down here.
This is not the place to have that. You
know, a nice soft football field or
something.
Despite the Bell team's impressive
rocket belt maneuvers, its 21se second
flight time is way too short for the
army.
There'll be no more funding until Wendel
Moore finds a way to break through that
time barrier.
While he tries to find a solution, a
whole new arena for individual flight is
opening up.
America's [music] Gemini space program
is taking men into a very different
environment.
In 1965,
astronaut Ed White [music] makes history
with the first spacew walk.
But it's soon clear that maneuvering in
space is difficult without some form of
propulsion.
As gravity in space is so weak,
a rocket powered backpack won't have the
same limitations as on Earth.
While the original rocket belt only
lasted for 21 seconds, people looking at
the technology realized that it could
work for up to 2 hours in space.
So, the engineers come up with this, an
astronaut maneuvering unit.
>> It's powered by the same hydrogen
peroxide fuel that the rocket belt was.
It has many rockets on it. And each of
these rockets only produce about six
pounds of thrust, but it's enough to
actually propel the astronaut.
>> And the unit is also able to rescue an
astronaut in the vacuum of space. It's
possible to just spin out of control.
>> If an astronaut was in the unfortunate
situation where they're freely tumbling
in space, they actually have a safety
switch. And when they push this safety
switch down, it stops all rotation
gently so they can resume their mission.
>> This ingenious device is just the
beginning of space maneuvering
technology.
But back on Earth, Wendell Moore is
still trying to extend the flight time
of his rocket belt.
As he wrestles with this problem, his
once [music] top secret device finds a
new role.
It takes to the air as a novelty [music]
crowd-pleaser and is an instant hit.
Whether it's racing a car at high speed
or flying up the football field at the
first Super Bowl.
In an age when technology is delivering
the American dream, the rocket belt
becomes a symbol of the future.
>> It was wonderful, very exciting.
They went to the World's Fair. They just
traveled all over the world and people
were so thrilled.
All the children of that time were
watching the Jetsons which had some
things like this. I I think that made
people think that what we had been
dreaming for so many years was a
reality.
>> Even secret agent 007 has to have a
rocket belt.
>> James Bond gets in a fight in the
chateau. He runs out on the balcony,
throws on his rocket belt, and escapes.
And that's what we were there for is to
fly off the balcony and down the street
and land next to the Aston Martin.
>> 20-year-old Willie Suttor shares the
stunt role with one of [music] his
colleagues.
He says, "This James Bond stuff," which
I'd never heard of, is going to be big.
[music] Mark my words. And he says,
"You're going to be able to tell all
your friends you are in a James Bond
movie."
The rocket belt continues to wow the
public wherever it flies.
But all the while, its inventor, rocket
engineer Wendel Moore, is trying to work
out how to keep a flying soldier in the
air for longer than 21 seconds.
>> One of the natural reactions of
rocketeers is to get more energetic
fuels.
that was rejected right out of hand
simply because they're poisonous.
>> So Wendell Moore considers the example
of early pioneers in vertical takeoff.
They're experimenting with jet power.
In the 1950s, his colleagues at Bell
Aero Systems had come up with an
ingenious design [music] using tilting
jet engines which swivel into position
for normal flight.
They're a distant forerunner of what we
now know as the jump jet.
Jet power also inspires an even stranger
experiment funded by the US military.
This gleaming flying saucer is
officially known as the Avro car.
Looking like a UFO, its technology
actually borrows from the early fan
driven flying platforms.
This giant Frisbee gets its lift from a
central turbo fan.
taking its power from three jet engines.
But despite an investment of millions of
dollars, the Avro car doesn't live up to
expectations.
It can barely get off the ground.
The project is shelved in 1961.
But this doesn't put off Wendell Moore.
He's convinced he can satisfy the army
by using jet power to increase the
flight time of his rocket belt.
>> So the second generation was to create a
jet belt with an air breathing jet
engine rather than a 21-second rocket.
>> The key advantage [music] of an air
breathing jet engine is it uses less
fuel than a rocket. But what Wendel
Moore needs is a miniaturized version.
Working with Dr. Sam Williams, one of
America's top jet experts, they develop
a jet engine small enough to fit on a
man's back.
>> And that was the heart and soul of the
Bell jet belt.
>> Two tanks of kerosene fuel the miniature
jet engine. As the fan sucks in air,
some goes to the combustion chamber. The
rest is used [music] to cool the hot
turbine gases to protect the pilot.
The powerful jet exhaust flows out of
the two nozzles to lift the flying
soldier into the air.
Wendel Moore reckons this engine is so
efficient it can keep a soldier in the
air for up to 25 minutes.
He persuades the defense department
[music] to fund a prototype.
For the next four years, the jet belt is
put through intensive tests using a
safety harness just in case.
The military are impressed. Even during
these initial trials, the miniature jet
engine seems as good as Wendel Moore
predicted.
With the jet belt still in development,
he's already working on ways to adapt it
for the flying soldier.
Wendell came up with what we called the
pogo stick, which was a standon. No
straps, no stand, no nothing.
We flew the first prototype as a rocket
machine because the jet engine hadn't
[music] been developed yet.
The Pogo had a key advantage for the
battlefield. Without a pack on his back,
a soldier could just land and move
quickly into position.
The ideas keep coming. They even take a
chair out of the office canteen and turn
it into a flying chariot.
The jet engine was going to fit between
your legs under the seat. The seat was
going to be the fuel tank and it would
have a plexiglass bubble.
Finally, the jet belt is ready to move
from the safety of the test hanger to
make its very first free [music] flight.
The dream of the flying soldier is about
to become reality.
[music] On April the 7th, 1969,
the Bell Jet Belt, invented by Wendell
[music] Moore, is about to realize a
dream held for 15 years by the US Army.
The Flying Soldier,
it's still a prototype [music]
and extremely heavy. When you got in it
on the stand and got [music] strapped
in, you fired up the engine and you ran
the throttle up to ground idle, which
was over 100 pounds of thrust, so that
it took 100 lb of the weight off your
body.
Then with another burst of jet power,
pilot Robert Coulter lifts effortlessly
into the air.
He flies around a 300 ft long course,
climbing to about 25 ft and traveling at
a speed of 30 m an hour.
Crucially, he stays in the air for over
4 minutes.
The jet belt was the answer to Wendell's
dream, being able to fly for [music]
prolonged periods.
It's still some way off from its full
potential, but Wendel Moore believes
he's at last found the best technology
for a [music] flying soldier.
Then, just weeks after his triumph,
Wendel [snorts] Moore suffers a heart
attack and dies at the age of just 51.
Without his driving force and with the
jet belt still only a prototype, his
former employers Bell Aeros Systems give
up on the project.
>> So the jet belt died a you know an in
glorious death. It only made a few free
flights.
>> But Moore's collaborator Dr. Sam
Williams carries on the quest.
Soon he puts a new chariot into the air
using the same miniature jet engine.
The Wasp, as he called it, is as easy to
maneuver as a flying platform.
But it doesn't catch on
because the army has finally decided on
its preferred device for a flying
soldier.
>> Roger. as soon as you
>> on the battlefields of Vietnam, the
helicopter [music]
comes of age.
>> And it's another bell design, the HU1
known as the Huey.
It is everything that the Army has been
looking for. It's safe, reliable, and
fast. was very flexible, very mobile,
and it could completely baffle the enemy
by changing the whole way that battles
unfolded.
>> It's true, these aren't individual
flying soldiers, and the Huey needs a
highly trained pilot,
but these helicopters are extremely
effective in combat.
In its very first battle, the Huey shows
what it can deliver.
>> American cavalry men riding not on
horses but on helicopters
confronted North Vietnamese regular
troops for the first time
and kicked their butts.
>> The army's 15-year quest for a flying
soldier is now over. But Wendel Moore's
rocket belt remains as an icon of
American technology.
>> They did a study where they asked
people, they said, "What superpower
would you most like to have?" And
actually men responded at 90% [music]
that they would like to fly.
>> Everybody could imagine at one time or
other being able to fly, you know, up
over the traffic or over the buildings.
I was just such a lucky son of a gun to
be in the right place at the right time
to have this opportunity.
You know, I got [music] to do all those
things.
A rocket belt for everyone remains a
science fiction dream,
but the idea of a flying backpack
continues to evolve.
In 1984, astronaut Bruce McCandless is
the first man to fly free in space with
no safety line.
>> Okay, here we go.
Now, that may have been one small step
for deal, but it's a heck of a big leap
for me.
This is really beautiful out here.
to move around in space. He puts his
trust in a gas propelled backpack.
And over 25 [music]
years later, astronauts still rely on a
similar device.
Every astronaut that goes on a spacew
walk, even today, wears a device called
Safer, which is a jetpack that allows
them to [music] rescue themselves if
they become detached.
They can simply fly back to the safety
of the space station.
Wendell Moore would have been proud. The
vision he had in the very early days of
space flight is still at work today.